The Philip Mackie Collection
The Philip Mackie Collection
1947 - 1999, predominant 1950 - 1985
MAC
Solent University Library
Mackie Philip 1918-1985
163 boxes (12.5 metres)
British screenwriter and producer Philip Mackie was born in Salford, Lancashire on 26 November 1918. He studied English at University College London, graduating in 1939. After serving in the army in World War Two, he worked for the Ministry of Information, producing documentary films. From 1954 he began a career as a writer, publishing a novel, Hurrah, the Flag! (1957), in addition to scripting several works for theatre and the BBC. He served as Granada Television's Head of Drama from 1958-1962, and then worked primarily as a freelancer for the rest of his career. Many of his productions are adaptations of classic works (Maupassant [ITV, 1963], Raffles [Yorkshire TV, 1977]) or based on the lives of historical figures (The Caesars [ITV, 1968], Napoleon and Love [ITV, 1974]). His best-known work is probably The Naked Civil Servant (ITV, 1975), an adaptation of Quentin Crisp's autobiography. Mackie died on 23 December 1985.
This collection holds the papers of the writer Philip Mackie, including scripts, correspondence, and other documents from his writing career, as well as some personal papers. The collection covers Mackie's novels, stage plays, films, and television productions dating from the 1950s to the 1980s.
The collection is securely kept in the library basement, and it is organised in box-files, arranged alphabetically by title of the work contained within them.
All of the contents in the archive are to be retained permanently.
This was a one-off donation; further accruals are NOT expected.
The collection was donated by Barbara Mackie in 2006.
Donation
Access is by appointment only. Please email: library.support@solent.ac.uk
Television--Great Britain--History--20th Century; Screenwriting; Film-making (Motion pictures); Screenplay writing; Film scriptwriting; Motion picture authorship.
- Literary Papers, 1952 - 1985; 1999; MAC/1; Solent University Library; Mackie Philip 1918-1985; 151 boxes (11.5 metres) plus scattered items
  Philip Mackie (born Salford, Lancashire, on 26 November 1918 and died Swindon, Wiltshire, on 23 December 1985) was a British film and television screenwriter. His works include The Caesers, Raffles, Mr Rose, The Naked Civil Servant and more. The Philip Mackie Collection was donated to Solent University and comprises scripts, notes, personal letters and diaries (often with annotations by hand).
  Papers that relate to literary output of Philip Mackie. The majority of items are typewritten scripts used in the production of TV programmes or films, but also included are notes and letters relating to these works and to his play and novel.
  The literary papers are loose and unbound screenplays organised in boxes.
  All of the contents in the archive are to be retained permanently.
  This was a one-off donation; further accruals are NOT expected.
  Access is by appointment only. Please email: library.support@solent.ac.uk
  Screenwriting; Screenwriters; Screenwriters - Archival resources; Mackie Philip 1918-1985
  - Miscellaneous Articles, Notes, and Professional Papers, 1947 - 1980; MAC/1/86; Solent University Library; Swinson Arthur; 7 items
    Miscellaneous articles, notes, and professional papers by Philip Mackie.
    Detailed contents:
    A copy of Monthly Review, published by the Central Office of Information: Films Division, from August 1947, containing Mackie's article Production History of a C.O.I. Film.
    Television plays: subject and treatment, which appears to be workshop material prepared by Philip Mackie for TV Writers School. It contains a brief biography of Mackie, a discussion of the nature of TV writing, and practical exercises. It is accompanied by a letter from the TV Writers School (dated 22 June 1960) asking Mackie to produce lesson material, and by similar material, already used by the school, written by Arthur Swinson.
    An untitled critique of The Man with the Movie Camera, a Ukrainian silent documentary film, directed by Dziga Vertov, 1929.
    Notes on the supernatural, taken from books including Strange Powers and The Occult by Colin Wilson.
    An arbitration by Mackie, on behalf of the Writers' Guild of Great Britain, of a dispute about screen-writing credits for the 1976 film Crime and Passion, whose earlier title was An Ace Up My Sleeve.
    An article for the TV Times, written December 1980, introducing his series Cover.
    Held in boxes 126, 128, 149, and an unnumbered box labelled Finances 76.
    IMDB page for Crime and Passion (1976)
    Swinson Arthur
  - Miscellaneous Ideas, 1952 - 1982; MAC/1/50; Solent University Library; Rakoff Alvin Film director; Brabourne John 1924-2005 Film and TV producer; Sheers James C Film producer; Haggarty John Writer; British Screen and Television Writers Association; Shindler Colin b 1949; 1 box plus several scattered items
    Papers relating to various ideas for films, novels, etc. by Mackie.
    Contents include:
    -- Outline and Synopses for a film, As Good as a Feast, by Philp Mackie and J. C. Sheers.
    Story Outline for The Missing Aunt, by John Brabourne.
    -- Synopsis for a film about Dr. Barnado, sent by Mackie with covering letter to Ursula Winant. [There are also notes on Barnardo in a notebook in box 143.]
    -- Suggestions for the format of Alec Guiness Theatre, apparently a proposed series of teleplays, drafted by Mackie in 1957.
    -- Typewritten notes from a writing course held in 1957 by the British Screen & Television Writers Association. The notes appear to have been distributed at the course.
    -- Four typewritten pages of suggestions for potential US TV shows drafted by Mackie in 1952.
    -- Typewritten draft treatments for a feature film entitled Fog, or Fog Warning by Mackie and John Haggarty.
    -- Outline of a story called The Brain, by Mackie.
    -- Notes by Mackie for an updated and anglicized version of the French Robert Macaire stories.
    -- Notes and draft script for a play titled variously, The Room or The Guilty.
    -- Typewritten script for The Fisherman's Wife, by Mackie based on a story by the brothers Grimm.
    -- Synopsis of a film entitled Down River by Mackie.
    -- Letter dated 11 July 1955 from Mackie to Benjamin Fisz of Golden Era films offering suggested improvements to the scrip and story of Hell Drivers, which was eventually produced by Fisz in 1957, apparently without incorporating Mackie's suggestions.
    -- A treatment for a film version of John Wyndham's The Day of the Triffids prepared by Mackie and Alvin Rakoff, with a covering letter from Kaydor Productions returning the typescript.
    -- Notes on the novel Jubb by Keith Waterhouse, evidently with a view to turning it into a drama of some sort, in a notebook. [In box 143].
    -- Correspondence (1976) between Mackie and Taurus Film relating to a grand project dealing with the European Renaissance. [In box 126].
    -- Correspondence (1979) between Mackie and Hollandia Filmprodukties relating to a proposed TV series abut Han Van Meeregen, the Dutch painter and forger. Included is a treatment for the series by Samuel Meijering [In box 127]
    -- Correspondence (1976-1982) between Mackie and Peter Hopkinson relating to a series about the English in Malaysia, variously titled Blood Count, Samarang, and The Eagle and the Dragon. Included are various synopses and treatments. [In boxes 126 - 128]
    -- Correspondence and a synopsis for a teleplay called False Witness, which is intended as part of the Armchair Thriller series.
    -- Correspondence relating to a potential teleplay about Diaghilev. [In box 127].
    -- A letter from Michael Ashe (1982) detailing several 'notions', i.e., plot outlines, for the series Hourglass Thrillers that he was trying to put together. [In box 128]
    -- A letter from Ian Warren (1981) discussing the possibility of Mackie working on a series to be called Butterfly Bay, or, The Last Resort. Included is a bible for the series by Rick Searle. [In box 128]
    -- Letters from Colin Shindler (1984) about Mackie writing for a mini-series called Maximilian in Mexico. Included is a treatment for the series, written by Shindler. [In box 129].
    -- Letter from Stephen Ujlaki, HBO, (1983) about Mackie writing for a series set in Palestine a few years after the death of Jesus, provisionally titled The Inquiry. Included is a synopsis of the series, dated February 1982. [In box 129]
    -- Correspondence with Charles Bloch (1985) about Mackie writing a film version of the Vincent Cosgrove novel The Hemmingway Papers. Included are Mackie's notes on the project and a summary of the story from Bloch. [In box 130]
    Held in boxes 82, 126-130, 143.
    Rakoff Alvin Film director; Brabourne John 1924-2005 Film and TV producer; Sheers James C Film producer; Haggarty John Writer; Shindler Colin b 1949; British Screen and Television Writers Association
  - Miscellaneous Short Stories, approximately 1950 - 1954; 1999; MAC/1/85; Solent University Library; Mackie Cynthia; 3 boxes
    Miscellaneous short stories by Philip Mackie.
    A copy of Modern Woman, April 1950, containing the Mackie story If It's a Boy.
    A copy of John Bull, July 24 1954, containing the Mackie story Gino, We Love You. Also, part of The Star Weekly, Toronto, October 30, 1954, where the same story is printed as The Second Engineer.
    There are also two boxes of short stories in typescript form:
    - Donovan
    - A Helping Hand
    - Lady of Leisure
    - Piano and Drums
    - He was Her Man
    - Death in the Long Night
    - Right of Way
    - Come to the Ball
    - Mulliner
    - Beauty Queen
    - Going to the Huts
    - Twenty-One
    - A Change for Us Both
    - Miss Smith
    - Party Line
    - The Oleander Tree
    - The Best of Friends,
    - A Wife for Bernard
    - A Very Special Woman
    - I Love Everybody
    - The Language Problem
    - If it is a Boy
    - The Man without a Heart
    - What Do You Think
    - Someone to Talk to
    - Good Night, Sweet Prince
    - Temper
    In addition there are two short stories that appear to be by Cynthia Mackie, Philip Mackie's wife. One has the first page missing, but the other is called The Exhibition, and labelled "C. Mackie, April 1999."
    Held in box 149, new box 1 and 2, and box 86.
    Mackie Cynthia
  - Miscellaneous Verse, 1949 - 1954; MAC/1/84; Solent University Library; 30 items (approx.)
    Miscellaneous verse by Philip Mackie.
    Copies of Letters to Licensees from 1949, one of which contains a poem by Mackie.
    Copies of A Monthly Bulletin: a magazine representing the determination inside and outside the brewing industry to improve public houses, and to maintain an adequate licensing law from 1949 to 1954, with gaps and duplicates. Each issue has a poem on the back page by "P. M.", presumably Philip Mackie.
    Held in box 149
  - A Death in the Family, or, The Key of the Door, 1956 - 1973; MAC/1/27; Solent University Library; 5 boxes
    Papers relating to A Death in the Family, a 1956 BBC TV screenplay, and its later versions (there was a 1959 stage version called The Key of the Door ), including re-workings for a feature film version that appears never to have been made.
    Box 41: A copy of A Death in the Family camera script (with details of BBC transmission schedules - October 1956).
    Two copies of " The Key of the Door: dialogue treatment for a feature film", written by Mackie in 1961.
    Two undated typewritten scripts.
    Alterations and revisions of The key of the Door by Mackie, with a cover letter written to the director Alan Bridges on 3 Feb 1965, discussing a new version.
    A 1973 copy of the draft screenplay titled A Death in the Family (Or, The Key of the Door).
    Box 91: an undated script of the screenplay of The Key of the Door).
    Box 131, 141 & 147: Copies of A Death in the Family - camera scripts (with details of BBC transmission schedules - 19th October 1956).
    Box 141: A copy of what appears to be an earlier draft script (dated 12 August 1956) and titled A Death in the Family (98 pages)
    Held in boxes 41, 91, 131, 141, 147
    IMDB page for A Death in the Family
    Bridges Alan 1927-2013
  - A Marriage, 1971 - 1976; MAC/1/10; Solent University Library; approximately 17 items
    Papers relating to A Marriage, a play by Mackie originally broadcast in 1972 as part of ITV's Saturday Night Theatre, and to a version apparently revised for the theatre.
    Box 5: Four typewritten versions of a script, apparently for a stage play, with handwritten amendments. A letter (dated Feb 13, 1975) to Clive Goodwin thanking him for suggestions of revisions on the play.
    Box 87: 2 copies of a camera script for the TV version, and 1 typewritten draft script for the TV version, 1 typewritten script for the stage version.
    Box 143: A notebook containing notes on A Marriage.
    Box 145: Three copies of rehearsal scripts relating to A Marriage.
    Box 104: Programmes and promotional material from an Australian run of the theatre play; programme from the premiere at the Thorndike Theatre, Leatherhead, England.
    Box 126: Letter from Allan Davis 4 October 1976) discussing casting of the theatre play. Letter to Val May, Bristol Old Vic, discussing re-writes (15 May 1976).
    Held in boxes 5, 87, 104, 143, 145
    IMDB page for A Marriage [Related work]
  - A Nest of Spiders, 1954; MAC/1/43; Solent University Library; 6 items
    Papers relating to A Nest of Spiders, a proposed six part TV series by Mackie that appears never to have been produced.
    Includes draft scripts for the first episode and storylines for the remaining five episodes. It appears to have been under consideration for production, possibly at the BBC, as there is a memo from Mackie to D.S.S. [Director of Series and Serials?] accompanying the drafts. There is also a brief and critical handwritten response from another member of staff.
    Held in box 82.
  - A Season of Giants, or, Michelangelo, 1984; MAC/1/33; Solent University Library; 1 box plus scattered items
    Papers apparently relating to A Season of Giants, a 1990 US/Italian mini series about the life of Michelangelo. The series is titled Michelangelo in Mackie's outline and bible, which obviously must have been written in the very early stages of production, but Mackie is posthumously credited on the series according to the BFI's ScreenOnline database, so it seems likely that these items relate to the series.
    Two copies of a bible for the series (181 pages each).
    One copy of the outline for the various parts of the series.
    Correspondence relating to the production, including with Stephen Smallwood, CP Films.
    Held in box 52, 129, and 130.
  - A Sight of Diamonds, 1956; MAC/1/42; Solent University Library; 4 items
    Papers relating to A Sight of Diamonds, a film about diamond smuggling that Mackie did some provisional work on, but which appears never to have been made.
    Contents include an outline treatment for the film (34 pages), some handwritten notes, some typewritten notes based on articles about diamond smuggling in magazines, a four page treatment sent to a producer, named only as "John", in July 1956.
    Held in box 82
  - Across a Crowded Room, 1976 - 1977; MAC/1/78; Solent University Library; 8 items
    Papers relating to Across a Crowded Room, a teleplay written by Mackie that was broadcast on Yorkshire Television in 1978.
    - A draft script for Across a Crowded Room (1976)
    - A revised rehearsal script relating to Across a Crowded Room (1977)
    - Letters for and from Peter Willes, Brenda Loader and Marc Miller (all from Yorkshire TV) relating to script changes and revisions
    Held in box 138
    IMDB page for Across a Crowded Room
  - All the Little Animals, 1969; MAC/1/14; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Two draft scripts by Mackie for All the Little Animals, an adaptation of the novel by Walker Hamilton. The scripts were prepared for Granada Films in 1969, but it appears the film/teleplay was never produced.
    Held in boxes 8 & 86
  - All the Way Up, 1969 - 1970; MAC/1/9; Solent University Library; 1 box (10 items)
    Papers relating to All the Way Up, a 1970s film by Granada Films. It was adapted by Mackie from the David Turner play Semi-Detached.
    One script, with typewritten replacement pages and handwritten annotations.
    Two typewritten drafts of a novelization of the film by Mackie. A novelization was published in 1970.
    7 newspaper clippings (reviews, advertisements) related to All the Way Up.
    Held in box 4
    IMDB page for All the Way Up
  - Amends for Ladies, approximately 1960; MAC/1/41; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Two unbound typescripts (104 pages) for part of a novel entitled Amends for Ladies by Philip Mackie. The work appears not to have been published. Included is Part 1 and two pages of Part 2 of a projected four parts.
  - An Englishman's Castle, 1977 - 1978; MAC/1/24; Solent University Library; 4 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to An Englishman's Castle, a 1978 three-part BBC TV drama written by Mackie.
    Box 28: Various draft versions for An Englishman's castle (extra pages for part three, 3 copies of part one, 3 copies of part two, 4 copies of part three, all copies with different annotations).
    Box 30: Final edited versions of An Englishman's Castle as transmitted ( printed June 1978, 2 copies for each part)
    Box 31: Rehearsal scripts - An Englishman's castle: play of the week (parts one and three).
    Box 32: Rehearsal scripts - An Englishman's castle: play of the week (2 copies of part 2; 2 copies of part 3).
    Box 82: Brief notes in a notebook.
    Box 127: Correspondence with Innes Lloyd, BBC TV, about the scenario and scripts.
    Held in boxes 28, 30-32, 82, 127.
    IMDB page for An Englishman's Castle
  - Black and Blue. The Middle-of-the-Road Roadshow for All the Family, 1972; MAC/1/15; Solent University Library; 2 boxes
    Scripts for The Middle-of-the-Road Roadshow for All the Family by Mackie, which was broadcast as part of the BBC TV anthology series Black and Blue (1973).
    Various scripts are included: drafts, camera-scripts, and rehearsal-scripts.
    Held in boxes 9 & 10
    IMDB page for The middle-of-the-road roadshow for all the family
  - Company and Co., 1979; MAC/1/67; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Papers relating to Company and Co., a teleplay by Philip Mackie that appears never to have been produced.
    One full copy of the script and correspondence between Mackie and John Kershaw (BBC TV) about revisions.
    Held in box 135.
  - Conjugal Rights, 1972; MAC/1/12; Solent University Library; 3 boxes
    Scripts for Conjugal Rights, a three-part series produced by Granada TV in 1973. Included are draft scripts, revisions, rehearsal scripts and camera scripts.
    Held in boxes 7, 20, & 21.
    IMDB page for Conjugal Rights
  - Cover, 1975 - 1981; MAC/1/18; Solent University Library; 2 boxes and several scattered items
    Papers relating to the 1981 Thames TV series Cover, although it is referred to by the earlier titles, Victims and T. M. S. Limited.
    Box 22: Rehearsal scripts for Victims episodes 1-6, 1 letter including cast suggestions, script changes and corrections to Jacqueline Davis of Thames TV.
    Box 23: Revised reading copies for Victims episodes 1-6, 3 letters with script changes and corrections addressed to Jacqueline Davis.
    Box 119: Draft and revised scripts for T. M. S. Limited dating from 1975-1979.
    Box 126: Correspondence relating to the BBC's ultimate rejection of T. M. S. Limited. Correspondence relating to a novelization of T. M. S. Limited by Dulan Barber (David Fletcher).
    Box 128: Correspondence with Jacqueline Davis.
    Held in boxes 22, 23, 119, 126, 128.
    IMDB page for Cover
  - Death of a Guest, 1960; MAC/1/62; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Scripts for Death of a Guest, a teleplay by Philip Mackie which was broadcast by the BBC on Sep 4, 1960. It appears to be a re-working of Mackie's 1955 teleplay The Whole Truth. There is also a letter from the BBC, which indicates that Mackie was intending to turn Death of a Guest into a novel, though there is no external evidence to suggest the novel was ever published.
    Held in boxes 134, 147
    IMDB page for Death of a Guest
  - Dolly, 1973; MAC/1/3; Solent University Library; 1 box
    Scripts for Dolly, Mackie's dramatization of The Dolly Dialogues by Antony Hope, produced in three parts by Yorkshire TV in 1973. The dramatization itself is here referred to as The Dolly Dialogues. Included are draft and rehearsal scripts.
    Held in box 24
    IMDB page for Dolly
  - Drink, Doggie, Drink, 1956; MAC/1/59; Solent University Library; 2 boxes
    Scripts for Drink, Doggie, Drink, a teleplay by Mackie which was broadcast by BBC TV in 1956 as part of the Sunday-Night Theatre anthology series.
    Held in box 131 & 147
    IMDB page for Drink, Doggie, Drink
  - East Lynne, 1982 - 1983; MAC/1/23; Solent University Library; 3 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to East Lynne, Mackie's 1982 dramatization, for BBC TV, of the novel by Ellen Wood.
    Box 26:
    2 copies of revised versions of rehearsal scripts (each 286 pages long)
    2 copies of the letter to Colin Shindler (BBC TV), 2 letters related to filming East Lynne (to and from Susan A. McGregor, BBC TV), letters from fans praising East Lynne with a covering letter by Colin Shindler mentioning ratings and possibilities of repeats, Philip Mackie's invitation to the preview of East Lynne.
    1 invitation card for Philip Mackie for East Lynne's preview (opening show) on 16th December 1982 (BBC Drama Christmas special)
    Box 27:
    2 copies of draft for East Lynne, 1 with handwritten corrections.
    Box 29:
    3 copies of drafts for East Lynne (with handwritten corrections), one with a cover letter for Colin Shindler where Mackie says he used "a wonderful new invention of carbon paper" to write the draft.
    Box 128:
    Correspondence with Colin Shindler.
    Box 129:
    Correspondence with Colin Shindler, including an article about Ellen Wood written by Shindler for The Listener, and a letter about East Lynne sent to Shindler by Dr. Margaret M. Maison.
    Held in boxes 26, 27, 29, 128 & 129.
    IMDB page for East Lynne
  - False Witness, approximately 1978; MAC/1/68; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Scripts for False Witness, a teleplay in six episodes by Philip Mackie. It appears not to have been produced.
    Held in box 135
  - Film for Hamburg, 1983; MAC/1/65; Solent University Library; 4 items
    Treatments for Film for Hamburg by Philip Mackie. There is no external evidence to suggest that the film was ever produced.
    Held in box 133
  - Fuff, MAC/1/49; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A script for Fuff, a comedy in two acts adapted, by Mackie, from a work of Robert Thomas, probably Assassins Associés (1965). The script seems to have been prepared for production in the theatre, but there is no external evidence to confirm if it was ever produced.
    Held in box 110
  - Good Girl, 1974; MAC/1/21; Solent University Library; 7 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to the 1974 Yorkshire TV series Good Girl, written by Mackie. Included are original typewritten drafts, camera scripts, and rehearsal scripts.
    Box 34: Camera scripts (1 copy of episode 1; 1 copy of episode 3, 2 copies of episode 4 and 2 copies of episode 5)
    Box 35: Rehearsal scripts (2 copies of episode 3; 2 copies of episode 4)
    Box 36: Rehearsal scripts (3 copies of episode 1; 2 copies of episode 2)
    Box 37: Camera scripts (2 copies of episode 1; 2 copies of episode 2; 1 copy of episode 3)
    Box 38: Rehearsal scripts (2 copies of episode 5; 2 copies of episode 6)